Preliminary Inventory for the American Guild of Variety Artists Records WAG.095
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Guild of Variety Artists Records
1948-1981
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Guild of Variety Artists
Dunbar, Jerry
WAG.095
161 Linear Feet (161 boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jerry Dunbar, counsel to the American Guild of Variety Artists, in 1982. The accession number associated with this gift is 1982.002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The American Guild of Variety Artists was chartered in 1939 by the Associated Actors and Artistes of America ("4As") to represent "variety" entertainers--circus and vaudeville performers, comedy and animal acts, night club singers, magicians, such highly paid stars as Bob Hope, Bing Crosby, Danny Thomas and Dinah Shore and poorly paid "exotic dancers" at drinking joints. The White Rats (1900), the American Artistes Federation (1919), the Actors Betterment Association (1933), and the American Federation of Actors (1934) had all made attempts to address the poor working conditions of workers in this field through unionization. AGVA's immediate progenitor, the American Federation of Actors, had its charter revoked after the "4A's" charged it with mismanagement and misuse of funds. The AFA joined IATSE, confronting the fledgling AGVA with disputed jurisdictions from the outset. The decline of vaudeville, the impact of radio and television on live entertainment, and such problems as a rapid turnover of executive secretaries, charges of communism, financial difficulties, and recalcitrance of producers and agencies, beset the organization in its first decade. From 1942 through 1946, and again in 1947, the "4A's" held AGVA in trusteeship.
In 1948 AGVA regained autonomy and its first national convention took place. The business of building the union proceeded with additional problems--a jurisdictional dispute with the American Federation of Musicians that lasted from 1948 to 1952 until the jurisdiction in question was ceded to the Musicians; conflicts with sister theater unions; controversy over AGVA's new insurance plan. AGVA struggled for jurisdiction over television, one it could legitimately claim because such TV pioneers as Sid Caesar and Imogene Coca, who frequently performed in nightclubs, were AGVA members. AGVA produced a short-lived variety television show to substantiate its claim, but it reluctantly relinquished the jurisdiction to the Television Authority, which merged with the American Federation of Radio Artists to become AFTRA. In 1954 in response to a conflict with Ringling Brothers and Barnum and Bailey, the union created the AGVA circus to play opposite Ringling. AGVA took over the Brother Artists Association, which had been chartered by the "4A's" in 1939 to organize the burlesque field. Serious jurisdictional disputes with Actors Equity erupted over legitimate shows staged by Las Vegas hotels, topical reviews in Greenwich Village nightclubs, and Industrial Shows.
In the 1950s, Jackie Bright, AGVA's executive secretary, provoked the wrath of a faction led by Penny "Blondie" Singleton which accused him of running a one-man union, misusing union funds to pay a libel settlement against Bright and other pecuniary matters. With membership and income at a low point and jurisdiction shrinking, comedian Joey Adams was elected president. He promoted another AGVA television show that failed to get on the air, instituted AGVA Audition Nights in New York, Chicago and Los Angeles, and inaugurated the AGVA Entertainer of the Year Awards, a televised variety show emceed by Ed Sullivan with proceeds for AGVA's Sick and Relief Trust Fund. He lobbied successfully to have Congress declare AGVA Week in October 1961. Other attempts to increase the union's prestige and jurisdiction included a reciprocal agreement with the Mexican performers organization, attempts to organize rodeo cowboys and cruise ship performers, continued crackdowns on "cuffo" or free performances.
In 1962 the Senate Committee on Government Operations chaired by Senator John McClellan started investigations into possible AGVA links with organized crime. They revealed that a significant portion of AGVA's membership were "exotic dancers" who were actually "B-girls" (bar girls) or prostitutes, some imported under false pretenses from Canada, some held against their will. The Committee charged that AGVA had known of the situation since 1953 but had done nothing because the union wanted the girls'dues payments. Investigations centered on the Chicago area, but spread to other cities. AGVA's financial records were seized by the Bureau of Labor Management. The National Labor Relations Board ruled that AGVA's branches be reorganized as locals. Jackie Bright was suspended, resulting in intensified infighting, growing financial problems, and union administration by an interim committee.
In 1964 an anti-Bright faction took control of AGVA and attempted to improve the union's image and financial situation. It staged an integrated variety show in Birmingham, Alabama. It defeated Actors' Equity's bid for jurisdiction over Mike Todd, Jr.'s World's Fair Minstrel Show. Committees of performers attended contract negotiations to safeguard their rights. Many branch offices were closed or combined and employees dismissed in an austerity move. An anti-trust suit was filed against the Artist Representatives Association, a guild of agents in 1966. At issue was the percentage agents demanded from the AGVA members they represented. In concert with other performance unions, AGVA succeeded in getting the restrictive New York cabaret card law repealed in 1967. The union opened a Las Vegas branch for the first time in 1968 and closed its unsuccessful home for the aged in 1970. A new constitution reorganizing the executive board and lengthening officers' terms was adopted; and Penny Singleton, who had headed the interim committee, was elected executive president in 1969.
In 1970, AGVA was forced to borrow $100,000 to keep going. The "4A's" held hearings into AGVA's problems and considered revoking its charter or putting AGVA under trusteeship. Financial problems increased. More branches were closed resulting in lessening services. AGVA was unable to achieve agreements with ARA or the Circus Producers Association. Las Vegas hotels refused to sign AGVA contracts in 1972; the "4A's" took over the Las Vegas negotiations. Many members refused to pay dues, so the union's income was reduced to almost nothing. Fraud charges were brought against AGVA's 1972 Entertainer of the Year Awards; rights to the program were sold to Ed Sullivan Productions in 1975. In response to repeated calls from members for the "4A's" to take over AGVA, the AFL-CIO sent representatives to study AGVA's problems. By 1974 the union was broke. All but the New York, Hawaii, and New Orleans offices were closed, and the national headquarters faced eviction. A Federal magistrate was appointed to handle AGVA's finances. In 1975 when Penny Singleton was declared the winner of a bitterly disputed presidential race, her opponent, Eddie Rio, formed a rival union, the Variety Entertainers Guild of America (VEGA). VEGA drew away many AGVA members leaving membership at an all-time low of 6,000, down from 30,000 at its height in the Fifties. In the late 1970's, the union once more regrouped and managed to keep going with a small staff and limited membership, mainly entertainers in nightclubs and arena shows.
The difficulties AGVA encountered can be attributed, in part, to the transient and diffuse nature of its membership and their changing employment status. Employers interpreted the Landrum Griffin Act in such a way as to exclude from union protection variety entertainers who were deemed independent contractors. Without the protection of a closed shop, outlawed by the Taft-Hartley act, individual performers had little recourse when employers refused to pay social security or unemployment insurance. The variety field has been further eroded by the revolution in entertainment resulting from videocassette recorders and home box office. Despite these impediments, AGVA, like its sister theatre unions, has attempted to legitimate the stage as a work place by struggling to preserve the lives, livelihood, and sometimes even the limbs of entertainment professionals. From bonding performances to assure that performers in one-night stands are paid, to fighting for safe rehearsal floors for Disneyland dancers, AGVA has tried to establish minimum basic conditions for variety performers throughout the country.
Sources:
"A History of the American Guild of Variety Artists: Dissertation Proposal," by Lori Seward, NYU Department of Performance Studies. Eventually, Ms. Seward chose another topic for her dissertation.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the American Guild of Variety Artists have been grouped into series by function and format, and where possible, arranged in rough chronological order. The collection has not been processed or refoldered. The files, in their disorder, redundancy, and gaps, reflect the sometimes chaotic administration of the union. The collection documents not only AGVA's history, including its internal struggles, but also its role in post-World War II popular culture. Historians will also find insights into the content of members' performances, their working conditions, business relations in the industry, and long-term trends in entertainment from the impact of mass media on live entertainment, to the brief vogues of "amateur hours" and go-go dancers. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
The collection is unprocessed.
As a preliminary arrangement the files are organized into 9 series:
Missing Title
I. Minutes
II. Annual Convention
III. Nominations, Elections and Referenda
IV. Correspondence
V. Membership
VI. Legal Files
VII. Contracts
VIII. Financial Records, Welfare Fund Minutes
IX. Miscellaneous
Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Contracts; Financial records; Legal files.; American Guild of Variety Artists; Associated Actors and Artistes of America; Dunbar, Jerry
- Series I: Minutes
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Minutes, 1948-1979, 22 linear feet. Includes minutes of the National Board, 1948-1968; National Executive Committee, 1948-1969, 1979; New York Branch, Membership and Executive Committee, 1958-1974 (with gaps); Branch minutes from Providence, St. Louis, Toronto, San Francisco, Sarasota-Tampa, 1947-57 (sporadic). Minutes include actions taken, communications, election results, reports on branches and trial boards and other materials. In general, they are not comprehensive with many gaps and overlaps.
  - National Board, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - National Board, 1952-Jan 1954 (Box 2)
  - National Board, Feb 1954-Oct 1955 (Box 3)
  - National Board, 1955-1957 (Box 4)
  - National Board, 1957-Feb 1959 (Box 5)
  - National Board, Feb 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - National Board, 1961-1962 (Box 7)
  - National Board, 1963 (Box 8)
  - National Board, 1964-Feb 1965 (Box 9)
  - National Board, Feb 1965-Feb 1966 (Box 10)
  - National Board, Jun 1966-1968 (Box 11)
  - National Executive Committee and misc. National Board referenda, Nov 1948-Dec 1951 (Box 12)
  - National Executive Committee, 1952 (Box 13)
  - National Executive Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - National Executive Committee, May 1955-1956 (Box 15)
  - National Executive Committee, 1957-1959 (Box 16)
  - National Executive Committee, 1960-Sep 1963 (Box 17)
  - National Executive Committee, 1960-April 1965 (Box 18)
  - National Executive Committee, May 1965-1968, Mar 1969 (Box 19)
  - Constitution, May 1969 (Box 19)
  - New York Branch Membership (with gaps), 1965-1974 (Box 20)
  - New York Branch Executive Committee, Sep 1958-1959 (Box 20)
  - New York Branch Executive Committee, Aug 1964-Sep 1969 (Box 21)
  - Branch Minutes-Providence, St. Louis, Toronto, San Francisco, Sarasota-Tampa (with gaps), 1947-1957 (Box 22)
  - National Executive Board meeting transcripts (March 1-3, 1979), Mar 1979 (Box 22)
- Series II: Annual Conventions
  Series II: Annual Conventions, 1948-1969, 5 linear feet. Includes resolutions, proceedings and arrangements for annual conventions, and information regarding the 1967-69 conventions that were not held.
  - Annual Conventions, 1948-1952 (Box 23)
  - Annual Conventions, 1953-1957 (Box 24)
  - Annual Conventions, 1958-1962 (Box 25)
  - Annual Conventions, 1963-1966 (Box 26)
  - Information regarding the conventions which were not held, 1967-1969 (Box 26)
  - Convention minutes, 1949-1966 (Box 27)
  - Conventions, 1963-1965 (Box 27)
- Series III: Nominations, Elections, Referenda
  Series III: Nominations, Elections and Referenda, 1948-1975, 14 linear feet. Includes correspondence and result of mail ballots for delegate and officer selection and union policy resolutions.
  - Nominations and elections convention delegates, national board members, rerun election (1949), 1948-1950 (Box 28)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegates, national board, and national officers, 1950-1951 (Box 29)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegate, national board members, 1952-1954 (Box 30)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegates, national board members, 1955-1957 (Box 31)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegates, national board members, 1958-1960 (Box 32)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegates, national board members, 1961-1962 (Box 33)
  - Nominations and elections, convention delegates, national board members, 1963-1964 (Box 34)
  - Nominations and elections, conventions delegates, national board members officers, 1965-1966 (Box 35)
  - Elections, preliminary matters and related issues, and the Dick Jones affair, 1967-1972 (Box 36)
  - Elections, convention delegates, national board members officers, 1968-1969 (Box 37)
  - Elections, 1973 (Box 38)
  - Rerun election, 1975 (Box 39)
  - Referenda, 1966-1968 (Box 40)
  - Referenda, 1969-1971 (Box 41)
- Series IV: Correspondence
  Series IV: Correspondence, 1948-1975, 35 linear feet. Includes correspondence of officers Jackie Bright, National Administrative Secretary; Jack Irving, Executive Secretary; Russell Swann, secretary Treasurer; Penny Singleton, Executive President, on all aspects of union administration: jurisdictional disputes, organizing drives, negotiations and contract administration, branches. Also included are four linear feet of correspondence from the Chicago branch, including branch minutes, between 1962 and 1974.
  - Correspondence including associations and organizations, elections, branch offices, Jack Irving, Executive Secretary, 1948-1955 (Box 42)
  - Correspondence including television matters, branch operational reports, national executive committee, 1948-1954 (Box 43)
  - Correspondence of Jack Irving, Executive secretary, 1948-1954 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence including branch offices and national office, 1952-1956 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence including American Federation of Musicians, comptroller, bond department (national office) AGVA News, 1952-1956 (Box 46)
  - Correspondence including Theatre Authority, Las Vegas booking reports, 1955-1956 (Box 47)
  - Correspondence of Jackie Bright, National Administrative Secretary including Teamsters, membership, Italian and Hebrew Actors unions, 1955-1960 (Box 48)
  - Correspondence of Jackie Bright including Agents and bookers, associations and organizations, personal, 1951-1957 (Box 49)
  - Correspondence including inter-office memoranda, 1958-1964 (Box 50)
  - Correspondence, alphabetical by correspondent, 1960-1965 (Box 51)
  - Correspondence including inter-office memoranda, branch offices, various individuals, 1958-1964 (Box 52)
  - Correspondence including branch offices, 1962 (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 54)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 55)
  - Correspondence including regional surveys, 1969-1973 (Box 56)
  - Correspondence of Russell Swann, Secretary-Treasurer, 1970-1975 (Box 57)
  - Correspondence of Penny Singleton and Russell Swann including arbitration, bond list, 1970-1975 (Box 58)
  - Correspondence including immigration, branch surveys, 1969-1973 (Box 59)
  - Correspondence including negotiations, sick and relief Fund, 1970-1975 (Box 60)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1954 (Box 61)
  - Correspondence including inter-office memos and Welfare Trust Fund, 1971-1974 (Box 62)
  - National office including "Four A's" history, New York branch (1950s), files of Penny Singleton; AGVA charter, 1939, Late 1970s (Box 63)
  - Correspondence including employer correspondence, various shows, camp shows, forms, 1949-1954 (Box 64)
  - Correspondence of Jackie Bright including negotiations, 1955-1957 (Box 65)
  - Correspondence of Jackie Bright including performing arts unions, 1955-1972 (Box 66)
  - Correspondence including international bookings, other unions, branches (master file), 1948-1952 (Box 67)
  - Correspondence with performing arts unions, 1944-1953 (Box 68)
  - Correspondence with performing arts unions, American Federation of Musicians controversy (1950-51), 1948-1951 (Box 69)
  - Correspondence including American Federation of Musicians (1968-1976), Front Office business, Branches (Providence, St. Louis, Toronto, etc.), 1947-1978 (Box 70)
  - Chicago Branch files, including branch minutes (1963-1965), 1962-1973 (Box 71)
  - Chicago Branch files, 1966-1968 (Box 72)
  - Chicago Branch files including branch minutes (1964-1969), 1969-1972 (Box 73)
  - Chicago Branch files, 1967-1974 (Box 74)
  - National Office including Ronald Reagan letter (1949, Screen Actors Guild); blacklisting; Television Authority; Four A's; branch correspondence and minutes; rulings on outdoor entertainments, circuses, fairs, 1949-1955 (Box 75)
  - National Office, continuation of Box 34, 1949-1955 (Box 76)
  - AGVA Welfare Trust Fund minutes, 1980 (Box 76)
  - AEA: "Sesame Street Live" agreements, 1980 (Box 76)
- Series V: Membership
  Series V: Membership, 1949-1974, 10 linear feet. Includes a selected sample of correspondence from members. Although much of it is routine, the correspondence sometimes sheds light on the content of members' performances, working conditions and long-term trends in the industry. Of particular interest are the photos and resumes submitted during the years AGVA sponsored its Auditions (1958-60).
  - Membership applications, Baltimore-New York (A-L), 1949 (Box 77)
  - Membership applications, Atlanta-Hawaii, 1963 (Box 78)
  - Membership applications, Los Angeles-New Orleans, 1963 (Box 79)
  - Signed representation cards, 1975 (Box 79)
  - Inquiries re: membership, A-R, 1975-1980 (Box 80)
  - Inquiries re: membership, S-Z, 1975-1980 (Box 81)
  - Misc. membership correspondence, subject file, 1968-1970 (Box 81)
  - Membership Correspondence, R-Z and misc. correspondence, 1974 (Box 82)
  - Membership Correspondence (John Bunn's office), 1970-1974 (Box 83)
  - Auditions (photos, resumes, etc.), 1958-1960 (Box 84)
  - Auditions (photos, resumes, etc.), 1958-1960 (Box 85)
  - Dues books, New York branch, 1948-1969 (Box 86)
- Series VI: Legal Files
  Series VI: Legal Files, 1950-1980, 18 linear feet. Includes files documenting litigation, contract negotiations, and settled claims.
  - Legal Files, attorneys correspondence, 1950-1976 (Box 87)
  - Amended constitution, 1969 (Box 88)
  - Litigation including Harrah's Club (Las Vegas), circuses, misc. cases, 1964-1971 (Box 89)
  - Litigation, A-S, 1969 (Box 90)
  - Legal files including Disney on Parade, 1970-1971 (Box 91)
  - Litigation including Disney on Parade, Ice Capades, 1970-1971 (Box 92)
  - Negotiations, Las Vegas, 1971 (Box 93)
  - Las Vegas legal files, elections, correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 94)
  - Settled Claims, A-Z, 1960-1971 (Box 95)
  - Settled Claims, 1963-1966 (Box 96)
  - Settled Claims, A-B, 1964-1967 (Box 97)
  - Settled Claims, B-Inte, 1965-1967 (Box 98)
  - Al Fast, 1965-1967 (Box 98)
  - NLRB, Al Fast, legal files, 1966 (Box 99)
  - Settled Claims, B-R, 1966-1971 (Box 100)
  - Settled Claims, A-M, 1967-1972 (Box 101)
  - Correspondence, legal files, A-M, 1968-1973 (Box 102)
  - Legal files including Canadian AEA, Sesame Street, 1968-1980 (Box 103)
  - Legal files including Connie Francis, Ringling Brothers, 1973-1976 (Box 104)
- Series VII: Contracts
  Series VII: Contracts, 1955-1975, 49 linear feet. Includes contracts of individual performers, agencies, clubs, cruises, and booking reports.
  - Individual, 1955 (Box 105)
  - Agency, Club dates, 1969-1970 (Box 105)
  - Contracts including circuses, 1957-1963 (Box 106)
  - Exclusive Agency, M-Z, 1959-1963 (Box 107)
  - Contracts, A-Bu includes burlesque contracts, 1962 (Box 108)
  - Engagement contracts, Bru-Chu, 1962 (Box 109)
  - Contracts, Da-Do, 1962 (Box 110)
  - Engagement Contracts, Dr-Ge and misc. Contracts, forms, correspondence, 1962 (Box 111)
  - Contracts, Rod-Sm, 1962 (Box 112)
  - Contracts, Rh-Roc and Wa-Wi, 1962 (Box 113)
  - Contracts, T-Z, 1962 (Box 114)
  - Contracts, R-Z, 1966 (Box 114)
  - Agency contracts, regional booking reports, and contracts, 1962-1963 (Box 115)
  - Agencies, G-M, 1962-1963 (Box 116)
  - Engagement contracts, misc correspondence, forms, by performer, act booker, revue, 1963 (Box 117)
  - Booking reports by branch, 1963 (Box 118)
  - Booking reports, memos, 1963-1964 (Box 119)
  - Booking reports by branch, 1963 (Box 120)
  - Contracts, A-Bos, 1964 (Box 120)
  - Contracts, But-Dar, 1964 (Box 121)
  - Contracts, Das-Go, 1964 (Box 122)
  - Contracts, Gra-Kz, 1964 (Box 123)
  - Contracts, Lar-Mitch Miller, 1964 (Box 124)
  - Contracts, R-Z, 1964 (Box 125)
  - Cruises, A-Z, 1964 (Box 125)
  - Contracts, S-Tz, 1964 (Box 126)
  - Contracts, U-Z, 1964 (Box 127)
  - Contracts, Regulations re: Artist Reps, Agents, Ne-Riz, 1964 (Box 128)
  - Booking reports by branch, 1964 (Box 129)
  - Contracts, La-Liz, 1964 (Box 130)
  - Misc., 1964-1965 (Box 130)
  - Contracts, A-L, 1965 (Box 131)
  - Contracts, M-Z, 1965 (Box 132)
  - Contracts, A-Z, 1966 (Box 133)
  - Contracts, Non-franchised, A-L, 1966 (Box 134)
  - Contracts, Non-franchised, La-Q, 1966 (Box 135)
  - Contracts, Non-franchised, A-Pl, 1967 (Box 135)
  - Contracts, 1966 (Box 136)
  - Booking reports by agency, A-V, 1966 (Box 136)
  - Contracts, 1966 (Box 137)
  - Booking reports by branch, A-Z, 1966 (Box 138)
  - Contracts, agencies and agents, 1966 (Box 139)
  - Contracts, Chicago branch, 1966 (Box 140)
  - Contracts, night clubs, L-Z (by agent), 1966-1968 (Box 141)
  - Contracts, A-M, 1967 (Box 142)
  - Contracts, 1967-1968 (Box 143)
  - Misc., Chicago branch, 1967-1968 (Box 143)
  - Contracts, Las Vegas, 1970-1971 (Box 144)
  - Contracts, Chicago/Milwaukee, 1970-1974 (Box 145)
  - Contracts, Las Vegas, 1971 (Box 146)
  - Misc., 1971-1974, 1979 (Box 146)
  - Contracts, night club by booking agent, 1971-1974 (Box 147)
  - Contracts, Po-Z, 1974 (Box 148)
  - Contracts, Las Vegas, A-L, 1974 (Box 149)
  - Contracts, Ringling Bros.-Z, 1974-1978 (Box 150)
  - Contracts, Individual and Company, forms, regulations, 1976-1978 (Box 151)
  - Contracts, B-S, 1964-1972 (Box 152)
  - Cruises, 1964-1972 (Box 152)
  - Contracts by Club, Q-Z, minimum basic agreements, 1970-1975 (Box 153)
- Series VIII: Financial Records, Welfare Fund Minutes
  Series VIII: Financial Records and Welfare Fund, 1949-1977, 5 linear feet. Includes audits, financial statements, membership data and minutes of welfare fund.
  - Audits/Financial Statements; Sick and Relief Fund; Agency Rules and Regulations; Membership data, 1949-1956 (Box 154)
  - Financial Records and Audits; Senior Citizens Fund; Sick and Relief Disbursements; AGVA Foundation, 1959-1968 (Box 155)